Guide to the Imre Forbáth diaries,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Imre Forbáth Diaries, 1900-1943
  - Journal 4: April 22, 1908-July 25, 1911 (Box 1)
    Spring of Ersekujvár
    Watering of Screw Factory, Starch Factory, and Goldberger Factory
    Waterworks in Ujpest
  - Journal 5: July 26, 1911 - July 20, 1914 (Box 1)
    Imre Forbáth is a professor at the Technical University. He works with four other engineers: Nagy, Pikler, Indy, and Wagner. The last two are still students. Technical innovations such as new pumping methods and Puech-Chaval filters are introduced. Forbáth travels to Switzerland, Italy, and Dusseldorf, Germany. He visits the Hygienic Exhibition in Dresden. While there, he attends a performance of Isadora Duncan’s dancers. He buys a Mednyansky painting. Forbáth takes out a 50,000-korona life insurance policy with the First Insurance Company. In 1912, his first book, titled Städtebauliche Studien, is published in Leipzig. At this time, he lives a very active social life. He is a member of the political circle of Lipotvaros and a delegate of the Independent Democratic Party. He is also in the leadership of the municipal Board of Works and is elected to the city council. After István Barczy, he is the biggest vote getter in this municipal election. He criticizes the Minister of Commerce for failing to submit the applications of Hungarian engineers to the Bosnian railroad on the grounds that there was a shortage of engineers in Hungary. He moves to a new house in Budapest, 46 Nador Street. He is financially successful. Imre Forbáth ends the year with a capital of 70,000 korona. He meets Olga Popper, whom he marries on February 1, 1913. On February 2, Rabbi Samuel Kohn performs the religious ceremony. On November 21, 1913, their first daughter, Eva, is born. Olga Popper’s family owns the Latzka and Popper Company. Forbáth and his family move to a new house, 3 Becsey Street. He visits the Picasso exhibition in Munich and an architectural exhibition in Leipzig in 1913. He studies low-income housing in Paris, Stuttgart, Vienna and London. He is invited to San Francisco for an Engineers’ Congress, but will be unable to go because of the outbreak of the First World War. Lloyd’s editor-in-chief forbids him to write for the Journal. Mor Revay asks him to write for the new Revai Lexicon. He wins first place for plan of Brasso.
    Dresden
    Dusseldorf
    Italy
    Leipzig
    London
    Munich
    Paris
    Stuttgart
    Switzerland
    Vienna
    Beothy
    Bezeredy, Gyula
    Biro, Elek
    Bodos (professor)
    Bohm, Agoston
    Copper
    Dohnanyi, Tivadar
    Duncan, Isadora
    Fabian
    Farago, Geza
    Ferrol, F. (Dr.)
    Fock, Ede
    Friedmann, Bernat
    Fuchs, Jeno (Dr.)
    Giovanus
    Godolloi, Lehel
    Gorkij
    Gospick, Alispan
    Grossfield
    Hainish, Michael (Dr.)
    Halasz, Frigyes
    Harrer, Ferenc
    Hary, Gyula
    Hausmann
    Hegedus
    Hevesi, Sandor
    Hosdzpotszky
    Ivanka, Imre
    Justh, Gyula
    Kaiser, Karoly
    Karolyi, Mihaly
    Kisfaludy-strobl, Zsigmond
    Klein, Gyula
    Kos, Karoly
    Kovacs, Aladar J.
    Latzko, Sandor
    Lenke
    Leonard (Mayor)
    Lipot, Hermann
    Loti, Pierre
    Lowenstein, Arnold
    Marc, Aurel
    Mezey, Gyula
    Mezossy, Desy
    Miklos, Gyula
    Pallenberg, Max
    Rados
    Ravasz, Oszkar
    Reich, Odon
    Rozsahegyi, Kalman
    Rupcsics
    Schiller
    Seneco
    Serenyi, Gusztav
    Shiffer
    Szamosi
    Szanto, Aladar
    Szereny, Zoltan
    Szigeti, Jozsef
    Szirmai, Imre
    Tornai
    Vigh, Janos
    Virag, Geza
    Weinberger, Miksa (Dr.)
    Writings of the period:
    A Budapesti hatosagi lakasepitesekrol / Gesetzliche Wohnungspflege (On Government Housing in Budapest); in his book published in Leipzig, Neue Freie Presse, Vienna, Journal
    A Budapesti munkaskoloniarol (On the Workers’ Community in Budapest); in his book published in Leipzig
    A kozmunka tanacsrol (On the Committee of Public Works), Fovárosi Hirlap
    A palyaudvarok rendezeserol (On the Train Stations), Budapesti Hirlap
    A Soroksari Dunaag kikötőve valo kiepiteserol (On the Building of the Port of Soroksár on the Danube), Lloyd, Vilag, Budapesti Hirnap
    Antwerpen (On Antwerp), Strasse, Halle
    Az Adria palota Erzsébet teri arkadjairol (On the Arch of Adriapalota of Erzsébet Square), Egyetertes
    Az Erzsébet sugarut és a kozponti városháza (The Erzsébet Boulevard and the Central City Hall), Fuggetlen Budapest
    Az Erzsébet sugarut terve (The Plan of Erzsébet Boulevard), Harrer
    Az Osztrak-Olasz hatarszelrol (On the Austro-Italian Border), Magyarország
    Az Újvidéki csatornázás (Canalization of Újvidék), Gesundheit
    Gross-Berlin (Greater Berlin), Lloyd
    Haupstadt in 1911 (The Capital in 19110)
    Schriften zur Forderung eines bessere Stadtebaues und der Kleinwohnungsfürsorge in Städten (Writings for Better City Planning and for Low-Income Housing), Leipzig
    Stadtabauliche Studien (Studies in City Planning)
    Székesfehérvár Asszonyvolgy (Székesfehérvár Asszony Valley), Lloyd
    Public presentations of this period:
    A folyami kikötők (Riverports), Committee
    A gyari furdok berendezeserol (On the Equipment of the Baths in the Factories), Nepfurdo Egylet
    A Soroksari Dunaag kikötőve valo tetelerol (On the Building of the Port of Soroksár on the Danube)
    A városepites kozegeszsegugyi vonatkozasai (Relationship of Common Health to City Building), Kozegeszsegugyi Szaktanacs
    Antwerpen (On Antwerp), Mérnökegylet
    Kereskedelmi Kikötők (Commercial Ports), Kereskedelmi csarnok (Commercial Hall)
    Kispesti allami munkastelep (Workers’ Community in Kispest)
    Segesvár csatornázása (The Canalization of Segesvár), Városháza
    The Question of Smog (Fustkerdes); National Public Health Committee (Országos kozegeszsegugyi tanacs)
    Városrendezesrol (On City Organization), Muszaki egyetem (Technical University)
    Vízvezeték és csatornázás (Canalization and Water Supplying), Székesfehérvári Egylet
    Expert in Kecskemét on Trauzl-Lefeber
    Expert in Nyitra, Gulin, Paskin, Vahovina
    Expert on Erzsébetfalva’s Water Supply
    Expert on Margit Island Beach
    Expert on Segesvár’s Sewers
    Expert on Spring Well of Margit Island
    Extension of the Water Works of Marossvásárhely
    Goldberg Factory’s watering
    Magyar-Dalmát Railroad’s Water Supply
    Plans of Nagybecskerek’s Draining
    Plans of Ujvidek [With Nagy and Pikler engineers]
    Power Plant of Nyitra
    Pumping Sewers of Székesfehérvár
    Székesfehérvár, Resica, Marodvásárhely, Albertfalva, Segesvár
    Trial on Water Rights of the Soroksar Avenue Distillation Plant
    Trials on Water Rights in Pluski on Drelulje and Jeszenka
    Water Refinement Plant in Nagyszeben
    Watering of Szabadka
    Workers’ Quarters of Kispest
    Works on Pécel Sewers
  - Journal 6: July 21, 1914 - December 26, 1914 (Box 1)
    Imre Forbáth and his wife are in England when the newspapers bring word of the outbreak of war, then of the introduction of conscription. They see crowds of people in front of banks trying to withdraw their savings. Urged by friends and family, they leave for home, stopping in Brussels and Hassel. Germany is on the eve of military mobilization. The railroads in Bavaria are protected by armed civilians. Masses of draftees flood trains and stations. Imre Forbáth is called up to serve as an engineer with the Seventh Division of the Thirtieth Infantry Regiment. He has to report for duty in seven days. The Seventh Division consists of 1,500 laborers divided into six parts, with an officer and an engineer at the head of each. Wherever the troops go, the people welcome them with flowers. The Seventh Division is taken to Przemysl. According to the diary, Polish Jews and Ruthenes are sent there as well. In September 1914, Árpád Tamássy takes command of the fort. The workers build barbed wire fences, trenches, and roads. Most of the civilian population leaves. The Russians attack the city, finally surrounding it at the end of September. Both sides suffer many casualties. The besieged troops have to come up with new ideas to supplement their diminishing supplies; they make matches and tie wooden soles to their shoes. On October 12, Austro-Hungarian troops relieve the siege of Przemysl and retake the height of Paportenka. On Christmas day, a mass is held for the troops on the frontline. In this diary, Imre Forbáth reports on the August 23, 1914 solar eclipse.
    Hassel
    Przemysl
    Czako, Pal
    Deer, Erna
    Fischer, (Dr.)
    Fodor, Gabor
    Kear (Captain)
    Krause, Tivadar
    Makrai (Engineer)
    Nonay, Dezso
    Richnowsky (Captain)
  - Journal 7 (Parts 1 and 2): December 1, 1914 - March 22, 1915, September 5, 1915 - October 20, 1915. (Box 1)
    The Russians had surrounded the fort of Przemysl again on November 8, 1914. Between Christmas and New Year, the fighting stops. The besieged troops are completely worn out and food is scarce. The laborers are armed with Wernil weapons and turned into soldiers. Weapons and ammunition are scarce. The army has to take care of the civilian population, including refugees.
    In the diary of Imre Forbáth, we get precise data on the number of laborers and soldiers, their pay, their food supplies, and what they do. According to his data, 25,000 Hungarian laborers are at the fort. Half of Forbáth’s division of 298 men build a road at Pod Masurani while the other half works at Makara Garai. The soldiers’ pay is 16 fillér per day. The civilians are overpayed for their work. There are 9,200 sick. Due to the harsh winter weather and the lack of food, the men become ill at work. Many freeze to death. At the end of 1914, Archduke Karl, heir to the throne, visits the front. He refuses to allow the surrender of the fort. An order forbids keeping records in writing as of January 7, 1915. The Austro-Hungarian troops sent to relieve Przemysl attack on January 23, 1915. They are defeated on March 20. Meanwhile, Na Gorach has fallen. The fort at Przemysl has been surrounded for four months and all the food has been used up. The fort is famously impregnable to military attack, so the men are willing to endure to the limit of their resources. The smallest portions are served. The horses are slaughtered, so there is meat, but nothing else; all other food, including bread and salt, is gone. On March 22, the Austro-Hungarians decide to surrender the fort. They blow up their cannons, weapons, and vehicles and await the fort’s new rulers. Forbáth’s entries stop here, but we know that the soldiers surrender and are sent to Siberia as prisoners of war. The Hungarian soldiers endured so much because they knew that the fort at Przemysl was the gateway to Hungary for the invading Russians. Their heroism became legendary.
    The second half of this diary, September 5, 1915 to October 20, 1915, is written in German and in stenography. Forbáth writes on top of his earlier entries, reversed, and starting from the back.
    Asimus
    Bednar
    Colonel
    Czapka
    Daver
    Epstein
    Ferenczy
    Fernchich
    Fieber
    Fliger (Captain)
    Habermann
    Hashinger
    Herbst
    Jausz
    Kisiliewski
    Krause
    Kreische
    Kusmarek, Herman
    Lonal
    Ludwig
    Makrai
    Mansfeld
    Milzer, Pista
    Nagy
    Nendtvich
    Nyiri, Ferenc
    Ordogh, Antal
    Országh
    Pechanek
    Prokopy
    Schafer
    Schaumberger
    Scherer
    Schwalb
    Schwartz
    Seidel
    Srocziszki
    Tamássy
    Tapay
    Theodorovics
    Vásárhelyi
    Vegh, Guido
    Vidas
    Werkfehrnelf
    Wodraschka
  - Journal 8: April 13, 1916 - August 12, 1916 (Box 1)
    Description: The diary is written in German stenography and is not deciphered
  - Journal 9: June 3, 1919 - July 24, 1920 (Box 1)
    No journals survive from the three preceding years. We can reconstruct the events of this period from recollections spread throughout Forbáth’s later journals. The prisoners of war from Przemysl were first taken to Tobol'sk in Siberia, then to the city of Petropavlovsk. Forbáth escapes (according to the March 6, 1920 journal entry). His friend, Beck, escapes in the same way. Eight months after the Bolshevik Revolution, Forbáth is still living in Moscow. The story of his captivity is written in German stenography in journal 8. He translates it into Hungarian, adds the story of his escape, binds it together with a Bible and photographs, and presents it to his son, Tamás, as a gift in 1928. He writes it out again in 1936 with the title “Diary of a prisoner of war,” hoping to publish it in England with the help of Samuel Hoare. Hoare has to deal with an unexpected political development, preventing him from meeting Forbáth.
    In this journal, Forbáth reports that his fellow prisoners Epstein and Tivadar Krause are still in Russia. He discovers that a box of his writings was left in a house at Upranskaja Ulica 64 in Petropavlovsk by A. G. Benzion, under the name F. Dezso.
    Imre Forbáth arrives back in Hungary from captivity just as war veterans are being called back to service. Forbáth is asked to perform office work. He feels no sense of belonging to either of the two sides, right or left. He draws up a plan to change the peace treaty in Hungary’s favor, with regards to the Danube as a natural boundary.
    The Fifth District Military Soviet wants Forbáth’s engineering office. They put strangers into every room of the family’s apartment. He has no work. Due to the administrative chaos, nobody pays for his previous work. He is still a member of the Community Work Committee, but he stops attending meetings during the Soviet period.
    On November 2, 1919, Forbáth’s second daughter, Zsuzsi, is born.
    On July 14, 1920, the Siberian prisoners of war return to Hungary; many thousands of people await them at the Eastern Train Station. Világ magazine interviews Imre Forbáth about the port of Csepel. In Közlöny, Forbáth’s very sick younger brother publishes an article “On responsibility for the money distributed during the Soviet republic.” Forbáth’s family has to turn to the American Relief Administration for help buying food. A family member who owns a textile factory in Kispest takes him on as a director.
    The journal has many references to “secret armed forces that attack Jews.” The attackers force Jews to take an oath to leave their house, city, and country, and never come back.
    Moscow
    Tobol'sk
    Barczy
    Bartok
    Beck, Jozsi
    Becsey
    Benko (comrade)
    Bogdanffy
    Buday
    Clark, George
    Csastkoczy
    Cseley, István
    Dienes
    Dubszky
    Farkas, Kalman
    Feherváry
    Ferbert
    Fleishman, Laszlo (Dr.)
    Garami
    Haubrich
    Herz
    Országh, Imre
    Joo, István
    Szoke, Joska
    Jozsef Hirling
    Karman, Todor
    Keller, Andor
    Kery
    Kramjansky
    Krassay, Jeno
    Laki, Imre
    Lovaszy
    Makay (comrade)
    Markus, Jeno
    Mihelfy
    Payer
    Potok, Armin
    Reinitz
    Revesz
    Schrerer
    Seifeld, Sandor
    Sugar, Vilmos
    Szilas
    Vago
    Varga
    Vásárhelyi, Dezso
    Vazsonyi, György Lukács
    Vazsonyi, István Szabo
    Zarka
    A Duna- kerdes és a Bekekotes (Danube Question and the Peace Agreement)
    A Proletar Diktatura Tortenete(History of the Hungarian Soviet Republic)
    Budapest szabadkikötő (Budapest Free Port), Lloyd
    Frage des Freihafen für Budapest (Question of Freeports for Budapest)
    Hadifoglyok házahozatala (Bringing home the War- Prisoners), Lloyd
    Munkaskerdesrol, Kozmunkak (On the Question of Work, Community Labors), Magyarország
    Szabadkikötők (Free Ports), Encyclopedia Britannica
    Zamard (Zamard), Stadtebau
    Canalization Plans of Esztergom
    Expert in the canalization of Nagyteteny
    Expert in the canalization of Duna-Tisza
  - Journal 10: July 25, 1920 - May 7, 1922 (Box 2)
    Forbáth still writes about atrocities committed against the Jews. The Soviet republic’s leaders are executed. Jenő Lipocz becomes prime minister. Vilmos Hilbert recommends a census of the Jewish population. The Christian national parties come to power, led by Ottokár Prohászka.
    Forbáth does not want to take part in political life ever again. Unable to get work, he has to sell off his shares. His private practice has been closed for seven years. In the Gresham coffee house, the Saturday Engineering Community meets regularly.
    The Foresta Corporation hires Forbáth to work in its operations cutting down forests in Romania. Later, the Nitrogen Company in Diciosanmartin asks him to take over its factory and save it from liquidation. In March 1921, the bankrupt factory’s chief director, Károly Koch, resigns. Forbáth takes his position. The next 17 years of his life are spent saving and consolidating the factory, raising it to the international level. Originally within the borders of the Austro-Hungarian monarchy, the factory had a contract with the monarchy’s Ministry of War. Following the Treaty of Trianon, Diciosanmartin has become part of Romania, and the Romanian Ministry of War wants to take over the factory. It is far larger than any similar operation in Romania, and the Romanians are convinced that the Hungarian government must be in control behind the scenes. Imre Forbáth, a citizen of Hungary, has to find a way to run a factory in Romania. He has to defend himself against the Romanian government, which targets him from the beginning. The case between the Nitrogen Company and the Romanian Ministry of War drags on for years.
    Imre Forbáth does business with Baron Willman and Dr. Freud (Austrian Minister of National Affairs), selling them nitrogen. He travels to Dresden, Berlin, Cologne, Frankfurt, Rotterdam, London, Belgrade, Sofia, Paris, Nagyszeben, Fogaras, Brasso, and Prague. Soderberg electrodes are used in the Nitrogen Factory.
    In September 1921, he has a reunion with his fellow ex-prisoners of war in the Bristol Restaurant.
    Edgar Milhaud, founder of Les Annales de la Régie Directe, sends Forbáth a letter from Geneva, asking him to be the Hungarian correspondent for the paper. Forbáth declines, giving the opportunity to one of his friends.
    The Regulation Plans of the Danube at Belgrade won second place.
    On November 25, 1921, his son, Tamás Forbáth is born.
    Belgrade
    Brasso
    Fogaras
    Nagyszeben
    Prague
    Romania
    Rotterdam
    Sofia
    Agoston, Bekenyi
    Baffe
    Balogh (Engineer)
    Dachler
    Deutsch, Dezso
    Enescu
    Gyarmaty, Victor
    Harver
    Hollosi
    Katona Rubovits, Mark
    Koch, Karoly
    Kommesman (Dr.)
    Kornfeld, Pal
    Kovacs, Geza
    Kramer, Jeno
    Kriesch, Al.
    Mikes, Camilla
    Orban, Ignac
    Rez, Richard
    Sandor, Janos
    Shabatiel
    Skin, Emil
    Stahelin (Dr.)
    Starcea
    Tacken (Dr.)
    Tornyai-Schopburger
    Vadasz, Sandor
    Vajda, Zs.
    Vantus
    Ziry
    A Nagylaki hatarkerdes (Question of the Nagylak Border; Note to the Consulate)
    A Zamardi furdotelep szabalyozasa (Regulation of the Baths of Zamardi), Städtebau
    Belgrad szabalyozasi terve (Plans on the Regulation of Belgrade)
    Budapesti kikötők (Ports of Budapest), Le Danube International
    Städtebau: Antant 1 (City Building: Entente, 1), Lloyd
    Städtebau nach dem Kriege 2 (City Building after the War, 2), Lloyd
    Újvidéki víz és csatorna (Water Supply and Canalization of Újvidék), Gesundheit Ingenieur
    Expert on Wagner Factory
    Expert on the Canalization of Nagyteteny
    Reconstruction of the Waterworks of the Danube at Szentendre
    Water Power Plant on the Danube at Moson
  - Journal 11: July 10, 1922 - November 4, 1924 (Box 2)
    In 1922, the board of directors of the Nitrogen Factory of Diciosanmartin resigns. The new board consists of Baron Paul Kornfeld and Kovács from Pest; Stein and Buchler on behalf of the Commerce Bank in Budapest; Goldfinger and Forbáth on behalf of the factory; two Dutchmen; four Romanians (one of them Dr. Joseph Boila); and one German (Alfred Herzfeld). The same year, they start a new chlorine factory and later, an ammonium sulfate factory.
    Outlets for the sale of the company’s carbamids are found in London, Hagen, Amsterdam, Rotterdam, Hamburg, Berlin, Cologne, Brussels, Bucharest, and Budapest.
    Imre Forbáth’s partners are: Acetylea, Vienna; Nitrogen Fertilizer Company, Belgium; Bayer Stickstoffwerke, Berlin; Thorn & Hadick Company, London; Bohm & Company, Berlin; Hirsh Kupfer and Metall AG, Berlin; Camindo, Berlin; Krauss Pachmann AG, Cologne; Kochler, Leipzig; Williem H. Miler, Hagen; Hamer & Les Pelzenburg, Amsterdam, Brussels; Klaber, Budapest; Hungaria Műtrágyagyár, Budapest.
    A trial takes place concerning the Nitrogen Factory’s fertilizer. A Belgian company claims that Forbáth’s company cannot sell cyanide because it does not have a patent for it. In fact, Forbáth has purchased rights from the patent’s owner, who lives in Cologne. He countersues the Belgian company.
    To become independent of currency fluctuations, Forbáth makes a deal with the Hungarian sugar industry that provides him with a steady supply of Dutch guilders. He negotiates with banks for the best rates on loans. For banks, the greatest risk factor is that the factory is in Romania.
    In 1924, all the factory directors in Europe meet to found a Carbide Syndicate. Dr. Wicklein performs an experiment, attempting to replace calcium chloride with nitrogen chloride. The case between Romania and Forbáth is still going on. The Romanian government wants a 200 million lei share and a 60-40 percent ratio in its favor. Until they reach an agreement, every government benefit, such as tax breaks, will be withheld. Forbáth has to prove that this request by the Romanian government is unlawful and exaggerated, and that the Hungarian government was never a shareholder of the Nitrogen Company.
    Berger
    Bohm, Thab (Dr.)
    Camindo
    Constantinus, Tanced
    Dounth (Dr.)
    Drailo
    Egri
    Ellinger
    Frank (Dr.)
    Goldfinger
    Hajdu, Arthur (Dr.)
    Hemelsnet
    Hoddle
    Hysgo
    Jorda
    Jovanovics
    Kejlinger, Mihaly
    Keller
    Monoilescu
    Pierson, Alard
    Pierson, Allan
    Rochmann, Pal.
    Romanesca, Bea
    Rosenberg (Dr.)
    Schwarz
    Sezitovszky
    Siebner (Dr.)
    Stefanescu
    Stein
    Stelian, Toma
    Suter
    Thoray
    Thusling (Dr.)
    Tybergheim
    Vajda
    Waldeek (Dr.)
    Wasserman (Dr.)
    Wicklei (Dr.)
    Zacharia (Professor)
    Zsiray, Miklos
  - Journal 12: November 7, 1924 to May 17, 1927 (Box 2)
    The Nitrogen Company’s attempt to fight nationalization continues. Imre Forbáth seeks loans and hopes to improve the credit rating of the company. He does business with the Creditul Industrial of Bucharest. The Nitrogen Factory is working at 50% capacity, which means that one wagon of carbide and four wagons of nitrogen are produced daily. The Romanian Industrial Ministry agrees to the contract that Forbáth made two years previously with Matos. In Diciosanmartin, an International Chemical Congress is organized.
    The Nitrogen Factory contacts the Zurich company Nitrum AG about building a sodium nitride factory, which would use a common method in which aluminum and ammonia are derived from ammonium nitride, and about the recycling of brown coal and tar. Delegates from Hagen, Amsterdam, and Vienna push for a world trade treaty on cyanide, which would keep American companies out of the European market. This is unsuccessful because the Americans are already behind the Bavarian company. The American Cyanide Company is a growing force in Europe.
    In 1925, the world’s leading companies come together in the courtroom of the Bayerische Stickstoff Werke. They are already discussing the idea of cooperating with the Americans. The Americans want to buy Forbáth’s Belgian operation.